doesn't need to do specific team them
the whole point is to watch thank you as
would you said few days ago when we
spoke about different people take
different approach to practice and then
how some people's approach involves
forsaking clarity hmm and if you if
you're sort of craving for clarity of
understanding I would say they're just
craving and dismiss yeah nobody denies
that it is craving if you have craving
for clarity that will result in clarity
understanding of the experience as a
whole then that craving has cancelled
itself there's absolutely no other
method well there is no method that you
could prescribe taking the result of the
method and clarity the only way to
arrive at it is to keep investing in so
that's what we spoke about the idea of
it was in the circus you know and
somebody different even if they don't
necessarily clear the knowledge if they
have a level of understanding
tamo unique they meet with the monks
they will be interrogating each other
not for the sake of argument or for the
sake of oh I know more than you do it
was really just to test their own
understanding and see if there is
anything that they haven't considered
because of which there may be no getting
the full picture
so the interrogation basically is done
for a second clarity
testing your own clarity the centrality
of others increasing your own blood even
like for example even in case you were
curious our course already don't need
anyone for their own private
if they end up talking Dharma to others
it makes them think about them which
mean makes them develop those principles
more than more than more so it's a
win-win really but the reason why you
won't see that done today is because
what it requires some degree of
understanding to start with otherwise
you just put the unit's bouncing ideas
of each other and that can't possibly
result in the knowledge before they get
too monstrous they think that monitors
can be a place where people do
investigate when they have discussions
together against the monastery and then
they sort of spend a bit of time then
they go so when do you have these
meetings when you discuss things well
and then the meetings that are there are
kind of super study groups which is
basically just a presentation of
information and then we all chip in with
our opinion or review on a certain topic
but it's really not like okay what what
does this mean because if we encounter a
contradiction well there must be
resolved but often I remember you know
people say already sub-tenants it means
that this and then he would point out
there are other significant they would
contradict that understanding not for
the sake of pointing out that that
cannot be the universal principle did
you discern from this because if it were
on universal it would be then understood
on every level but then people just go
silent if it's for the sake of your own
clarity and your own understanding
you must have stopped until there is a
big at least sufficient level of that
clarity at the time doesn't mean you
won't find contradictions later on but
certainly if you're aware that they are
you must make the word to to undo them
and that is literally the the most
direct way you can have good can in the
review and understand so I'm doing your
wrong views through through self
questioning you look for the meaning of
the universal experience
so across my mind you well we can be
arguing each other action nature
erection like obviously there were no
books about it all the time and it seems
to be the convergence point for
wholesome and unwholesome and there are
obviously many many views associated
with it and people inevitably have to
start with around beers but becoming
aware of the wrong views as your
starting point helps you then make the
effort towards I'm doing it you know
gonna this assumption that you find the
right view you could be on the wrong
views so I'm affected the wrong I just
need to keep looking for the right
answers and then I'll get the right view
right here is basically undoing your
views that are wrong that's how your
re-derive you and there's absolutely
it's inconceivable that those wrong
views would be undone on its own without
the effort of actually unscrewing them
and making them fade away
that's the detective everybody talks
about and the gradual shelving of the
ocean and so on you need to keep
applying that pressure and effort so
words your own wrong views and that's
how you undo them that's what they are
really versatile is well once under them
you can carry acquired but is this
common notion of or just do these
observances methods techniques practices
and then I'll have a magical experience
of the Rajiv
so interrogation action
what does what does various action
constituted is it in sale you're about
to do something physically go for a walk
using your body for walking is that
action in your physical movements or is
that action in the decision to walk even
before you start walking so where does
the action begin yeah you can say that
yeah the thing begins you say a plant
doesn't begin when it starts to grow
outside the soil hmm begins at its roots
you know begins their way it's rooted
that's very graceful so if you intend to
if you decide to walk outside and then
you start walking there walking is
secondary the walking is secondary
mother to see to the decision to walk
yeah it's a secondary in terms of its
it's more it's more grunt proliferate so
it sort of starts it starts with I mean
I suppose it is like there's a basically
this is possibility for going for a walk
is this like even before a decision is
made there's this that's a possibility
to want to start with a possibility so
say you see it starts with that not
start but like so so action is like me
there are these possibilities and like
think that that one possibility going
for a war presents presents itself it
buddy main just like just be kind of
bodily you may not even buddies they're
imaginary is there an action
I guess not unless yeah if you don't if
you don't choose that possibility then
though if you choose that possibility
but okay that's that's what question is
what is the question where does the
action start that choice so then there
can be no action without choice like all
of what you said is correct yeah exactly
you couldn't choose to act in a certain
manner if that's not given as a
possibility if you're if you're a
wheelchair-bound connie's your legs in
here possibility of walking has been
permanently removed but that's the
important point that's not where the
action starts and sometimes people not
necessarily differentiating that ends up
blending possibilities and things that
just arise in their mind on the level of
possibilities and they assume them to be
the action they try to get rid of it all
so yeah there is no action to walk or
rather choice to walk is not the action
the actual walking will be action of
walking which you maintain to the
presence of choice to walk so action
without choice is inconceivable that's
what was the reaction is intention
so intention to walk the choice that you
make the intention that's present hence
you were walking while that choice is
present and that's another thing how
people will just jump into the
assumption that the whole thing is
linear so you made the choice and that
choice is ended when you started walking
but that's absolutely not the case the
attention remains there in
intelligibility to every single step you
make you wouldn't know what to do next
you can no knowledge of walking no
intention to walk you will just set the
foot and then but you know did you know
the walk in involves moving forward but
using your limbs the people would also
tend to think the choice
it's a kind of explicit ah now I'll do
this yeah that's tensed talking in
itself as well yeah thanks
see extreme illusion or something yeah
so if you so so if you don't but then
there are occasions when you realize
that you're doing something and I didn't
actually explicitly go in awareness
going I'll stop I'll do this well then
actually so that's what I must have just
missed it was to get in there but I must
have just missed this that's exactly the
kind of metric pointer you will arrive
at would be where does awareness of the
choice come in yeah which is why the
whole like wakefulness that's either
what you said you know it's with people
start with you they think okay so only
when I'm super extra mindful did I make
a choice that's a mindful choice here
everything below that threshold or super
extra mindfulness doesn't constitute a
choice so I just must always remain
equally mindful to this like overloading
extent of I'm moving I'm moving and
touching I want to drink I'm drinking
I'm sitting and if I'm doing something I
didn't actually and and that's
unsustainable which is incidentally
mindfulness so that for basically we are
constantly making choices hmm without
absolutely being aware at the time that
there are there are sub yep so that's
the point there was gonna make it's the
the key to practice mindfulness it's not
to tailor your choices to your assumed
degree of mindfulness it's to remind you
refine your mindfulness to actually
discern the choices and they're already
there and being made so it's completely
the opposite direction but that takes
much more work refining your discernment
of the choices that are there enduring
because you're doing all these actions
as opposed to just sweep all that away
and now only what
is one decision follow on my mindful
presence of my every moment but I decide
what I intend and then you always have
to lapse from that kind of state but
instead of trying to fit your choices
into mindfulness you refining
mindfulness to start seeing all these
choices that they did on their own and
that's how you also get and that's what
this and the confusions basically
because it's hard to understand that if
you are unaware of a choice doesn't mean
he was unintentional I mean simply your
mind is so far removed yourself
awareness yeah so that's when people
don't kiss I must make unintentional
choices that count but you start with it
but you actually want to refine your
mindfulness then further and further to
see other slightly less intentional but
still on the level of the threshold of
intention choices that you're making so
how could you then for example you how
would you then for example practice
mindfulness practically how would you
how would you be mindful again no right
or wrong answer describe how you
understand it oh I understand basically
whatever understanding a person has even
if you don't have the fundamental
understanding it's a form of
understanding for them so the practice
then is to refine their understanding
get freed from contradictions or
mistakes and then take it further in
that direction not like that's wrong it
is the right answer
so from that probably there is no wrong
answer really is just accurate and less
accurate so you want to go about during
the day practice mindfulness how would
you do I come and ask how can I be
mindful for throughout a day how would
you advise me
paying attention to the to the things
that are already sort of happening such
as what you mean I don't understand that
like right now I'm on the city I'm
sitting I'm sitting on City but I do
intend to sit in this position in this
place so there's a there's a degree of
awareness even if I'm not fully
attending to the UM sitting so how does
that then what do you mean by paying
attention to that what you say paying
attention to that it's more like
reminding yourself
oh that already like whatever degree of
awareness is of what things that are
already there it's you were like oh sure
so how often do I have to remind myself
that it depends how often you sort of
drift away from it so every time one
would drift away as soon as they
remember technically - remind himself
I suppose if you can this but think of
it as like I'm drifting away that you
already know that you're drifting away
so so the act of reminding yourself what
would that entail say you remember that
you forgot wave would know that actively
minding we're doing it what do I remind
myself off what am i doing right now
what am I thinking right now hmm
so the present actions so can you say
then that can there be mindfulness
without actions
so I really think of or more regularly
they can there can be no mindfulness
without intentional basis so even if
you're restraining a physical action
intentional basis to act so that's why
everything would come down then to
discerning whether it is rooted in
wholesome one holds those intentions if
it's an awesome you don't allow the act
to take place in my body speech your
mind that's all the the sadhana he knows
his mind as effectively lost effectively
lost he knows mind effectively diversion as
he knows mind effectively diversion as
effectively diversion my god he didn't
go in South Sudan in a and tries to get
rid of it no he just needs to not act
out of it and that's already experienced
with mindfulness so yeah the rule of
thumb yeah trying to remind yourself but
not of some kind of or be here now in
the present moment but remind yourself
of what is your present situation if you
forgot about what does that means you
can start reminding yourself of the fact
that you just forgot so when you
remember that you lapse that's what you
remind us of all there is the experience
of forgetting right now because I forgot
so you stopped focusing then so much on
the content of what you forgot no I
forgot that I'm sitting you still seated
and you clearly haven't forgotten
completely because otherwise you
would've stood up but that attention
still there because the bodies to do
think could you say some goodbyes if you
say lose the context of your situation
you stopped being mine
mindful forget what you did you should
look at what you can also sell what are
the routes 19 you know what are the what
are the intentions present Bella that's
what is my attention brutally what are
the intentions well then it's that's
another thing isn't it because if you
are careless in regard to your
intentions you'll be intending of good intentions
you'll be intending of good intentions
and you'll be doing six different things
at once
now that doesn't matter that you can't
handle doing six different things at
once but they must be then unified with
one general intention so sometimes you
can actually if you don't have clarity
of your intentions you can be clarify
them by seeing what you didn't mean what
is the general context of all these
different things that I'm doing and then
allow that to maintain in your mind as I
thought that in yours on its own so why
am I sitting here why am I sitting right
here sir sir actions are always so
hierarchical yeah yeah you can always
you can sort of focus on a particular
you know I don't know I'm lifting the
cup I'm pouring the sure oh you go and
I'm just making coffee
exactly you don't need to worry about
the everybody but that is also why
people who just started practice who
don't necessarily know and who would be
focusing on every moment that's where
they do get some sort of release through
that but it does feel like you're
mindful certainly more mindful than
usual because if you are aware of the
action you're doing the intention that
is simultaneously present that is
implicit but see the problem is if you
don't know that you are supposed to be
looking beyond the action you're doing
and discern the present intention in
your mind then you just become a
mechanical who tries to sort of touching touching
who tries to sort of touching touching
moving pouring pouring lifting exactly
because you refuse to look what's
underneath because you think I must just
look at the surface of all these acts
but that's why initially there is a
degree of flood oh yeah this feels like
it works because you are in the generic
well you are implying the awareness of
your intention to do this but then
things will get complex things will get
faster harder to control and your
mindfulness is gone with it but that
would not happen if you remain mindful
of the intention to make a cough it
doesn't matter how quickly how slowly
you do it you are making coffee until
that's fulfilled all of your action will
be around that it's you be mindful of
before the root of the particular things
that you're doing yeah it's all even
your own your own attention attending to
the attending to the coffee
intention to fulfill this goal
singleness of their context singleness
of that purpose not singleness of every
aspect of your act
yeah it's like when when people go on
meditation retreats and do some kind of
they'll be very careful about how to no
sensations in the nostrils or something
yeah I was thinking I think for a lot of
people mindfulness is about like going
on a retreat and you know sitting in a
room together and focusing your
attention on your nostrils are you
breathing something and you're getting
people can you know get so absorbed in
that but they're completely forget the
fact that they have chosen to go on this
retreat for whatever reason and
everything that they're doing is
determined by that more general would
you be able to do any of those things
without a more general intention well no
no would you be able to they interesting
without implicit
leave the time I do is the doing those
things will fulfill your goal and
purpose oh yeah freedom from suffering
or hope will take through a particular
act of attending to my breath my baby
there the roots of my act hmm which
might be a wholesome based on creating
delusion which through attending my
breath that's general intention where
everything is routed will change will be
purified mmm won't be what it is
yeah yeah so it's here my act is rooted
in this mess yeah and it's big it was
massive and then I just attend to
something in it miss yeah and somehow
the mess is going to disappear yeah and
even if a person does not necessarily
explicitly think this the fact is that
you start with like I don't know what am
I supposed to do and then you choose to
do this out of that lack of knowledge
you already well you manufacture the
belief that what you are about to do
might possibly result in uprooting
basically the roots of your actions in
the first place yeah that watch is a
sinner is it a routine mmm I'm just
putting on Holi no there's no evens but
not even you know even addressing that
more general yeah and no matter that you
know a lot of practice policies that I
was addressing you either
that's the thing the practice that you
would be learning in the retreat center
would be you do this you do this you do
this it's absolutely no point at
anything like wait you stop and look at
the intentions of your actions so you
jumped into it out of a belief which
then automatically simultaneously
fabricated that implication that this
might work and helped me and now
everything is based on that magical
connection of doing random acts and believing that
of doing random acts and believing that
they lied to me will happen to you
so mindfulness of action is gonna
somehow needs to involve a recognition
of this distinction between general and
particular hand well how would you how
would you do that on a more practical
level for yourself for example so to
hear you recognize you can recognize
just asking yourself why am I doing this
well there's these particular things
that I'm doing but you can just question
I'm doing this well it's more general
but what's a bit like you said before
you sing down but your Y my 8y my same
here why am ia nurse and exactly you can
be the same Srilanka see me for
questioning like that you will also then
be looking at the well developing
knowledge you got your own actions why
am I doing this so you can sometimes say
why am I doing this all well because
such and such thing happened to myself
here but why did I choose those things
be the reason for my action right here
right now he'll always comes back on you
but if if my the weight of my attention
is placed on the roots hmm not that you
forget about direct but that's what this
might be wrong but the weight of my
attention it's not Caesarea placed on
the roots then if it makes sure it does
it make sure that the acts that I do and
what particular exercise do are poised
in line with it yeah intensify did not
contain you then yes I don't have to
worry about what you yeah act I'm doing
because it's been driven by this
intention that I have which I'm
maintaining by
so how do you place the weight of your
attention up to the root of the
attention how do you do that how do i
how come one do then well if I said at
the end that's it now hey what sir I
think it's a same question how cannot
maintain awareness of my attention so
that all my actions are driven by that
at the root to me right so how can you
maintain that
yeah we're in recognition of the
motivation of all these particular goods
exam yeah so how do you do it
that's what I'm asking you go to learn
not to know what the context is of you
actually how to do that so can you give
an example of a context in regard to the
action so it's somebody who's listening
to for the first time we know like okay
that's what I got to look for this what
would it be the practical situation
well giving its own footwork what's
happening right now yeah okay go ahead
describe it on basis of an example
sir if I if my say my intention
why am I sitting here I tend to and
cover our own understandings so why do i
why am i doing that
so I'm freedom from suffering
can almost feel what's the first next
question what's my intention to be free
boobs every to be to be unbothered
switches what is bothering or it's
happening do you want to be free
suffering cuz you don't want to suffer
so that I know how you can ask and
further yeah the question closed upon
itself so if you are then if that's the
that's the context of my actions
mm-hm reason why I'm among these one
sitting here these one eating stayin
alive breathing and so on it's cuz you
don't like stuff right
I'm trying yeah I don't want to
something yeah yeah they're like so all
the suffering bothers you yeah well let
that stop me in itself but before we go
into that so how do you then do it back
into what you said well I do well this
seems to do what you're doing let you
remember that we all can how to remember
yeah Thomas on what what to remember in
order to maintain the mindfulness or the
particular actions because you were
talking about shifting the weight on to
the root of your attention which means
that which you are attending you want to
shift some weight from it on to wear and
I'm asking how know necessarily Y which
is cuz you won't be free from suffering
well how do you go about it
okay I want to talk about you know you
own you so money seconded yeah this is
what it is exactly not yeah no I just
like again same what I asked if I want
to learn how would you tell it
practically how can I do that yeah but
what is the theme of my actions how do i
how am i aware of the theme well the
theme is in the background the meaning
of my meaning
so what you're basically saying is if
you don't forget the motive behind your
own present enduring action you are
dividing the weight or shift in some way
back after the origin of what you're
attending is it just the process of
asking yourself why I'm doing this here
we start with that yeah so why am i
doing this just asking that question a
recognition of what navarre you and you
and you and what you're doing right now
so like I'm sitting here and talking or
like I'm going for a walk again
everything sure everything will be
funneled into the most general purpose
I'm a man can will be free from
suffering but that might be a big to
I removed for somebody when they just
start so you want to find slightly less
general basis for your act so why am I
going for this walk because I haven't
moved I haven't moved my body for three
days I was sick so I need to move ok
that's your motivation and then use is
there anything wrong with that
motivation no so I can go for a walk
where do I go for a walk and and so on
that's that's another thing you should
be considering that but if exactly
sometimes oh because I'm kind of bored
and restless in my cootie like oh so I
am acting out of unwholesome basis of
restlessness so simply questioning
yourself about the motive where is
you're actually you're about to do or do
you have been doing when you if you
caught yourself at a later stage where
is it rooted and that's all you need to
do in order to clarify the situation you
they need to every time arrive at the
answer that because you want to be free
from suffering in you're a monk although
that's gonna become implied yeah see
like now I want to avoid acting out of
your will why because from the other
point of view that's unwholesome and
that prevents the fulfilment of my goal
of being a monk and being free from
suffering that's what on a practical
basis here why am i doing what I'm doing
right now oh because of this simply
maintaining the knowledge of why are you
doing whatever you're doing that's your
mindfulness that is basically beginning
and the ending of mindfulness but you
have to sir maintaining your knowledge
but you have to question you question
your motives squared emerges a day that
generates the knowledge yeah I wish you
do I'm just thinking is there a danger
that some people when you when you ask
yourself why am I doing this oh there's
a danger to psychology yeah that's what
I mean yeah well you all read you and do
it you just come up with some sounds of
scientific that's why I keep insisting
you have to find motivation yeah so it's
not with why not as in what it's not
finding it's going on that's making me
do this it's why am i doing what what's
the meaning it's not about finding the
answer yeah
in as much as finding the motivation
which is then the answer yeah oh why am
I doing this because my parents never
love you exactly well that's not the
motivation that's you chose that why did
you choose that to be a reason because
other people have parents they don't
love them and they don't do the same why
did you make these choices so that's why
mean there is a danger of psychologizing
in as much as there is a danger if you
don't do it at all of completely
ignoring it and just following the
mechanical methodical practice of
robotic technique but yeah even if you
start psychologizing you ask yourself
that oh why am i now providing all these
explanations for this so it's asking why
and but also taking responsibility
responsibility did you can't have no
yeah no choice back your head sir having
the knowledge of the motivation behind
right attention behind things you attend
yeah knowledge of the roots of your
attention yeah so then also that means
brings it back to all the folks we've
been doing before about 34 awareness
it's on I mean you can't attend on the
same level the knowledge because of
which you're attending all this person
particular things so that's why you
can't or rather if you do start
attending to that knowledge in a as if
it is an object of your attention means
then you're motivated with something
else so you need to discern motivation
without needing to attend to it at the
expense of everything else and that's
why mindfulness will result in knowledge
because that's what knowledge is keeping
things at the back of your mind that you
already know without having to think
about them all the time that's exactly
what knowledge is when you don't know
something you have to think in attend
and try to figure it out once you do
automatically recedes into the
background and becomes the significance
experience when he will call it the
point is you don't have to be going
around thinking that 22 is 4 2 and 2 is
4 2 + 2 is 4 cuz you already know and
you know what you know how to add things
up you understood the principle of it
you're not thinking about it and that's
the point here to understand the
principles of anita understand the
principle of dukkha because it all
revolves around a sense of self like
having non mindfulness of these things
involves the the cell field having
mindfulness of these things are prudes
this up view cuz he makes it redundant
did you mean like says somebody who
someone they could drive does nothing
think about driving yeah of course well
and they can't think about the driving
see because they don't know how to drive
they can think about how to move the
stick how to twist the wheel - how to
press the pedal when they understand as
in develop more general understanding of
these particular actions that's when
they know how to drive and then all they
think about is driving they don't think
about every particular movement of the
hand but see it's like people when
people people act normally like that and
then they get into practice and then
they try to undo this and become focused
on every little thing you do at the
expense of what you're doing because
that's what you would like to believe
that that's what meditation is moment to
moment experience ignoring the bigger
picture which is already a moment
experience that's why I keep saying like
before I've ever you know the one
pointedness some people play referred to
Samadhi but it is - way to ways you can
go about it they can be one point in us
in terms of you focusing on one point so
hard it you forget about everything else
absorbed yeah oh you discern at one
point that includes all these other
things within it so which one does it
sound better focusing hard on one little
instance so I simply have no recognition
of any other instances or finding the
fundamental instance did already
includes all
and given that the Buddha gave so many
simple examples and similes of a gate
keeper you don't go chaser on every
individual instance of a person in the
city you stand at the gate you know that
inside that's all you know I have a
knowledge that all these people are in
that's it that's Samadhi
that's the practice but that's harder to
do because you have to question yourself
and they will bring anxiety that would
bring doubt there will be and that's
exactly what the five hindrances then
become such a thing it's manifested
through to proper practice but if I just
tell you know just focus on your
nostrils focus on touching with soles of
your feet as if walking means I want to
touch things with my soles know walking
means I want to move I want to walk all
these are the particular actions you can
look at will be seen correctly only if
you don't forget the general context of
your intention to walk that persists for
the duration of your active walking and
again it's that principle of the whole
of the past you can only understand what
part is from the context of the whole
you can't understand the power you know
you cannot stop the past then you put
together to get the whole the way around
you have to start with the whole to
understand what the part is and even if
sometimes you don't know what the whole
is the fact that you're assembling parts
to find the whole yeah means you have a
recognition that they must be a whole to
these parts but what people hope is like
this absolutely zero knowledge of a
whole and somehow are magically right
with the knowledge of the whole based on
these random parts and doing so that's
why yes being instructed hearing the
Dhamma as in getting the sense of the
context that must be developed does give
the direction to all those individual
actions but how individual those actions
will become well that depends how wrong
your views are because you can say I was
becoming a monk and warrick wearing
robes anything once a day - all those
are individual actions towards your
practice of freedom from suffering but
they are not from the same level as
individual actions of touching touching
moving moving sitting sitting feeling
thinking thinking speaking speaking
those are also individual actions but
you see how for much more than a
misguided they are misguided because
what the more you commit to it the
further away from the context you drift
and exactly that can happen to monks as
well when being a monk becomes about
having my perfect rope perfect stitch
I'm such a beautiful disciple I always
put on gents cloth perfectly and I walk
so soft there speaks or softly and I'm
Elena still mentally basically so that's what
still mentally basically so that's what
mean all these are individual actions
but it's whether you know that you're
supposed to look for the context behind
him or not that's when you become a like
a career monk well it's about appearance
it's about this it's about serving and
doing it and not about understanding the
context of your actions kind of context
of the suffering easier it is
that's why steel about the bottom is the
first factor people they're all get very
sort of derogatorily translated as as
rites and rituals because you know
nobody's silly enough to worship rites
and rituals as a vehicle to
enlightenment but it isn't seen about
the bottom Assamese virtue and duty so
me doing the verge doing the duty
without understanding the context of it
means I'm factored by things I'm doing
that's it now imagine you take that even
further and I start doing all these
mindless meditation techniques and
everything else and literally you
basically completely cement any access
to the direction where the context of
your actions are so you broke your
context your motivation hmm govern your
actions yeah so if you protect it does
that's higher mind you're at higher
motivation that big yep with your life
yeah do worry about much else is that
because I was like everyone that you get
you have to learn how to drive before
you can get there so what is what is it
I want to develop kindness loving
kindness some is good I'm just getting
used to what kind things are pick up the
theme of kindness
and it hold and then make that developer
theme has the thing that I'm my shining
light in my life is that context but the
sign of kindness that's what I
concentrate that's what I compose most
of my life in without needing to sort of
go through like daily repetition
particular actions of expressing
kindness to everyone that is smiling and
doing all these things no kindness means
absence of your work because you will be
naturally doing things yeah
because that's what they rooted yeah
that's the theme of your leave of the
game is kindness thing whatever I come
to contact with which I I will come into
contact with things cuz I'm eating I'm
going to toilet and speaking as people
sick but if doesn't matter what things you
but if doesn't matter what things you
come across and against if a backdrop
against those things is the theme that
you invested effort in developing it
theme of kindness Noel will can seep in
the into this particular actually
because there is a lower level yeah 35
if you are unclear about the theme of
kindness that's it
lack of clarity will then give rise to
what last immersion delusion units
always gives you a wave is a nice to
these things a painful thing comes up
okay know anything hmm well it will test
your clarity of the theme of kindness
yeah so much dose to insult me yeah but
then if you still recognize it doesn't
matter how powerful somebody's trying to
push through the gate all I need to do
is stay the gate I don't need to fight
them where they are or change them
inside I just need to stay the game so
you just need to stay at the level of
the theme of kindness and you will then
and again that can only be developed if
you keep doing it if you keep practicing
it then you develop confidence in it but
that's thingy someone oh so if you you
protect that mind of kindness which now
you you be maintaining for a while
someone comes to insult you you don't
have to worry about what you responsible
exactly because it will come from
place of where you are always situated
if that mind is clear you've not lost
sight of that mind of kindness and and
losing sight just - it means muddling
the knowledge it's not losses because
sometimes people we say lose sight or
don't lose sight means I must think
about it must attended losing sight
means being unclear about it so just
have to declare afire because it's
always something that I can't quite
attend to it's not like a level of your
sight sight which is on the level of
your attention it's like it's different
[Music] having certain techniques on how to deal
having certain techniques on how to deal
with people in soldier hmm okay they say
this I'll say well so a friend it seems
that you you need something you know
what are your once nonviolent
communication and you have to do this
thing I have a lot of aggression in you
yeah so you have to do all these
techniques it's trying to rebuild the
context regulating things that you would
think becoming out of their context one
on any person would speak like this but
you don't know that because you're
already angry so another angry person
would speak how well why don't I remove
my anger and then whichever where I
speak will be a non angry way of
speaking rhaggy and others might be witness to
rhaggy and others might be witness to
you and then start writing down all the
things that you do when you respond yeah
he says this he asked the person that's
Oh exactly yeah
they might even disapprove you they'll
say no that's not how non angry person
would speak yeah like there was happen
in the sentence with the other hand who
was fully realizing but was upsetting
because they are so you got angry they
so yeah what people just assumed that he
was angry they just assumed he was angry
because he was speaking in such a harsh
manner that they call him sending to the
Buddha able to call him said start
talking to him so he's in the hunt so
that's I mean it's not like how you
speak and often they're either there like the
and often they're either there like the
whole holy life companions in the Holy
life that are pleasing to listen
pleasing to sort of be with and so
friendly so kind so so generous so
helpful with evil wishes ignorant of the
wrong view and dead ones are really hard
to live with
you don't speak pleasantly they're rough
around the edges but they're of the
right feel then the other ones you're
both are you the Buddha clearly says
which one's more important it's the view
so you can you can if you can refine
your behavior to not upset vast amount
of people great but don't confuse them
to be the practice don't confuse that
there was somehow that he generate the
context that you have no knowledge of
how can that happen I have no knowledge
of the context of absence of your will
yet I'm hoping to regenerate it through
reading the nonviolent communication
books and just sort of going through the
motion of softly spoken tailored words
so you just have to learn how to look in
a different direction yes Yanis vision
in a more general in a more encompassing
direction and which is just inquiring
into motivations yeah that's the that's
the gateway and that's why everything is
I said when we started is converges on
action converges and action is basically
within motivations if it's a good action
or bad action so it's not about oh I
must stop doing that of course you stop
doing things that are against the
precepts but then people don't know
where to draw a line and then whatever I
must stop doing it well that becomes
your form of doing abstaining from doing
everything else it's what I'm doing all
the time 24/7 and it's a very
frustrating frustrating position to me
shirin's you can't stop doing the only
way to stop doing is to understand the
roots of your action first you need to
replace the bad doing with good doing
and then get to understanding but just
doing the good will not free from the
nature of action
yet doing the good practicing like me
for example like a non-violent
communication technique that's it's
always coming it's all coming from based
on anger yeah that's way your anger
becomes implicit in your practice to be
free from anger sorry I'm just left
alone system following on exactly what
you just said though and from all your
saying before if you are clear about
your motivations like fully clear in
which case there won't be any delusion
in regard to the context that you're in
then in a sense you don't need to worry
about actions anymore there's no kind of
you know need to sort of do anything
yeah exactly
becomes effortless because it is because
it ever since erection yeah now that's
the absence of action and that's how you
also go beyond doubt as well if you
don't clear you know you're anxious you
will be doubting it if somebody starts
questioning it you start doubting it
yourself but doesn't mean how much you
doubt the content you won't be affected
by the darts towards the content yes
you're not doubtful in regard to the
motivation they made you perform that
content in the first place so you will
not be able to doubt it oh maybe I
could've done this or this but doesn't
matter I know why I've done it it's when
people are unclear about that that's
when you just doubt the steam it all
over but it's all since the end of
action you fully develop ears I mean in
case you're not the opposed because
because it's just intentions giving rise
to these other intentional actions and
that's it there is no be choice based on
ignoring the context it's being made
towards those actions which is what the
Trillian situation is you know Castagna
cuz the petition is always making
individual choices of more very
particular levels of particularity hmm
well there's no guard it right at the
top right well he's making choices
because it's fine he was not aware that
the choices can be made without
in him to be the making them so he's
ignoring the general or rather his
unaware has no clarity in regard to
general context yeah
that means he immediately implies then
that he is the sole criteria for making
decisions yeah failing to see that those
decisions can be made only because they
were given as as simultaneously reason
options for you to attend and then
choose an account oh but you know that
then what else is there making choices
oh it's only me and I am hence I must be
so then choices that he makes a choice
is written in his self of you but if you
recognize that even I am making this
choice you realize because in the
general context that provided you with
these options you realize it's all
rooted in you the roots of your choice
are not rooted in you which that means
the action they were rooted in your
choice cannot be rooted in you either so
the protrusions context is me but you
can pick this up you can like we can
easily see that when you ask yourself
what's the context
you always find it is like it's kind of
not me it's like it's it's the context
is always prior to my own particular
choices that I make those choices
well then we'll make some Incas spin
around but if you were to start from a
neutral position that answer is true but
poutine is not in the neutral position
so in order for him to arrive at that
the choice is already there the only way
to correct your abilities to first
accept the choice is first on him and
then this choice that to me is then on
what inside they said in some columns so
the Lord you say that that but that so
okay so I yeah so I'm responsible for
these these particular choices but those
choices are always made within context
that's always already given sure sure
you ask yourself then next question yeah
this seems to be clear to me I seem time
understood it am I completely free from
suffering if the answer is no means you
haven't fully understood it there is
still a proposition of action means
there is still absence of ära handshape
so yeah no I'm not denying that there
are different degrees of understand
this but you shouldn't stop short until
you're completely beyond it
since we're sort of like why the house
is done on a practical level mm-hmm
say that see like saying where your
motivation is when it comes to an action
you have to have a degree of awareness
wholesome and wholesome to say this is
right this is yeah yeah sure but that's
see everybody has a degree of awareness
now you can then refine it even further
everybody knows what's bad to do in your
body to kill to steal to cheat to lie
and so on so you everybody knows that
certainly everyone who's practicing the
Dharma so then show without compromising
in that principle you can study finding
it further understand the root of it
sure this petition is no knowledge of no
it's virtuous so he has some sense of
something being right something wrong he
has a sense of virtue yeah the point I
was sort of like I was getting that is
that like he went for the sense of work
to like you and if you say you have
doubts about sense of oho to a certain
degree of some aspect or another and
like in order to develop that you sort
of start with not sure what the exact
translation is here your thought is a
sense of shame fear of wrongdoing
yeah so fear of wrongdoing and sense of
shame already implies a degree of action
isn't it like you mean like
see like it implies virtual as in like
sense of virtualizing you know well it
implies fear of unwholesome yeah but the
practicality of it is that the fear of
from doing it should sort of like you
have a certain event of we're aware of
awareness of well where your action is
rooted much like any action like well
it's a it's a context for directions
it's a context for abstaining from wrong
actions developing fear of wrongdoing
means in developing context of not
acting and awesomely cuz you have fear
of it so out of the fear of wrongdoing
then your actions won't be as
unwholesome yeah so it's a context for
your actions and for absence of
particular rather unwholesome actions
otherwise you wouldn't be abstaining
from unwholesome actions if you don't
have fear of wrongdoing you would just
be doing it why are you not doing it
then why are you practicing restraint
because you develop feed off of normal
restraint because you recognize that to
be the basis for the right practice so
then why do I want to practice over
because I wanna be free from suffering
and so on
so yeah that's why it's useful not they
go around neurotically and fear
everything whatever I done is but this
also is is unwholesome no it's
recognizing it things rooted in lust
aversion distraction or unwholesome and
you value absence of those unwholesome
things so much that you fear the
possibility of the presence and if
you're afraid of their presence you like
it will be possible for you to act two
words there if you lose the fear of the
possible of their possibility then yeah
you start getting closer and you start
acting towards it and you refine your
awareness of your actions also what
exactly - basically refine your
abstinence from our wholesome actions
and then abstinence of unwholesome
actions means abstinence from
perpetuation of unwholesome principles
of craving lust and so on and now that
you're not perpetuating them they start
fading and once they do they sort of
thin out you can see through them much
better but that's another thing like if
there's something say there's like a mad
rabid dog on the other side of the gate
and now you know the risks implications
of that kind of animal you feel it you
wouldn't go near it you make sure the
gate is boarded and that's it you've
done your bit and you feel safe where
you are and you have a fear of that
which is in the other side in case you
get there so you make sure you don't get
them but I imagine you don't have that
context of that fearful animal oh I'm
quite curious about this dog let me go
and see and then you make all these
actions the result exposing you to that
thing which you could have prevented if
you develop fear properly in regard to
property
so that's why I like the the will
encourage monks to sort of contemplative
chanting Heights provides little
satisfaction much greater danger because
if has a presence of central object its
seen implicitly dangerous you won't have
to all now I have to pull my mind back
from it no your mind already won't be
there cause it's dangerous lacking the
perceptions of danger yeah mine will
start entertaining it because its sense
of shame they're kind of signals did
you're going in the river very far which
is going against what you trying to
maintain yeah yeah I'm trying to
maintain a mind of loving-kindness and
I'm now I'm going to beat someone up hmm
because I feel uneasy I feel shameful as
it's the signal going off so going
against it that signal will be more
powerful when there is a greater
discrepancy that you were about to
create with your action yeah so somebody
who's been practicing sense restraint
that's how you also get to increase here
they're not about you start by doing
absence of sensuality more and the more
you do it the more you value it so now
the prospect of doing it requires even
greater discrepancy of your action to
reach that further away and which means
then that the alarm will be much higher
as if somebody who just yesterday
decided to give it up tomorrow he might
feel a bit bad but he doesn't feel the
full weight of the danger of giving back
into those things it's like a buffer
zone yeah alarm alarm alarm alarm alarm
alarm alarm and the more you practice
the bigger it is which means the less
likely is that you're going to cross it
without becoming aware of what you're
about to do is they call the Guardians
yes the guardians of the world yeah it's
like it that you can become more
sensitive to you feel shamed taking
sure seeing the danger under the
slightest fault yes the suitors would
say yes what I mean doesn't mean you
become neurotic sometimes might happen
is a side effect but you can grow out of
that but it means actually maintaining
that context is it even any significant
thing such as taking extra sugar that's
often you're not breaking any rules but
why because I just have pure craving
desire for sweetness sweet taste no no
no no physical purpose no physical
necessity or benefit nutritional benefit
I simply want this taste and if you use
that as a criteria to not act and you
would be ashamed when you're about to
act so that's why means like seeing the
danger in the slightest fault
not like all over look look look see
this room is this and they're you
folding a city cover that's an offense
that's an offender that see that's a
fault no means recognizing where the
faults are when things are rooted in
greed aversion delusion even if on paper
the Vinaya says yes you can have all the
sugar you want because it's offered you
still feel ashamed because you don't
need it and yet you take it for pure
sensual satisfaction that's it that's
why from there the attitude that point
of view there are no loopholes in vinaya
because there are no loopholes to
craving but if people just follow the
letter of the rule oh well see the
building specify this means I can do it
whether you can do it or not should not
be rooted in whether it was written over
or said by the Buddha sugar is it you is
it rooted in my Creed a version delusion
then you should just make that look good
and that's again what we said there is
this okay so I can't keep all these
hundred something rules the Hmong
country but it says can you just keep
zactly so if you have no context
whatsoever you need this formulated vinyasa to
you need this formulated vinyasa to
create that absolute outer edges of the
boundary but you taking that to be the
goal in itself that's why you never
actually get to understand where those
actions are rooted in where the problem
is so it's basically just like rounding
up the scent of slightly
like you can't spend your whole life
being extremely strict and lineal so not
be paying any attention to weather why
I'm doing it salsa Munoz I mean this so
affected by your own veneer but still
protect you to an it to an extent it's
still better than being under strain
yeah but but but still you need to make
that your training wheels
yeah yeah that's why you can go beyond
being you see everything unwholesome Lee
is not Cielo you know your virtue in
sensory strain does not prevent little
unwholesome just prevents the expression
of it so it's like you got sick you
caught some bacteria did now you have I
don't know fever as a result of it and
all these are the symptoms and now I
can't of those symptoms you keep
aggravating your situation further you
go and jump in a cold pool to cool down
your fever which actually makes your
bacterial even worse but you don't know
that you just deal what you see in front
of it so the first thing you have to do
is stop jumping in the cold pool they
will elevate your fever that will help
you feel it but I can be the cause of
the fever so you stop practicing
restraint control the symptoms but now
if you think that all you have to do is
abstain from going out into the cold
water because you won't agree with the
fever and you think that would be enough
to the nut root the root cause of the
fever as well that's not going to happen
so vinaya and see lies that outer edges
so basically okay don't aggravate the
aggravated symptoms anymore stop here
but if you think that stopping there
will also then clear of the symptoms
they won't happen only approaching the
cause will then remove the symptoms it's
the same like - I don't know why I'm
complicating with a different similarly
similarly of th the wounds on your skin
it with the game first thing you have to
stop scratching scratching will not
uproot the bacterial infection sorry
cessation of scratcher will not approve
the bacterial infection but he was
certainly stop spreading it and then you
can apply medicine for the underlying
cause of that which made you
in the first place and that's basically
the vinner stops you from making things
worse but taking that to be practice for
uprooting it well that's extremely wrong
view it's a first fetter syllabus and
unless you're been Denis you won't get
the right view let alone free yourself
from last an aversion later on say if
you're confused about where my action is
you can always know in regards to the
word traversing I'm not doing this
exactly so you can be confused in terms
of a particular level well is this okay
overall is this wholesome or unwholesome
if it's not unwholesome then okay wait
and you might get clarity in regard like
that and we take like it's nothing wrong
I'm not stealing this sugar but am I
taking it cuz I really need it because I
really didn't have enough calories what
I'm taking it fuel it clearly for
pleasure sake well as I said if you're
unsure then don't do it as a rule of
thumb I don't know if what I'm about to
do I know it's not unwholesome to the
level of breaking rules and so on but on
a more personal level in a more
immediate level I'm not sure whether
it's desire or without desire then don't
do it if there is a disagreeable
experience in regard to it means desire
was involved if you generally then don't
care means there was no desire involved
because you wouldn't be affected by
saying no to things unless you have like
a desirous mind towards them so if
you're doubting its most likely rooted
in design hence doubt it is an
unwholesome thing no Tina so I must stop
doubting i'ma stop thinking oh I must
clarify my mind to go beyond this doubt
so the doubt cannot enter it you can't
control the doubt doubt is another
symptom it's rooted in lack of clarity
and when I say clarity means lack of
recollecting in a lack of understanding
not lack of information because
sometimes people yeah sometimes you
don't know enough so you read the rules
and so on but sometimes people that's
all they do just need to keep rereading
and be told the same thing on and on and
on and on to help them deal with it down
that's not dealing with it
just feeling it further you want
external authority to remove the doubt
for you because you're not seeing for
yourself where directions are routed so
that's only practically you can check
that general context what you're about
to do is it clearly unwholesome then
it's not negotiable
oh I want to go for a walk why is it cuz
I'm Restless what cuz I need some
exercise if you're not clear well then perhaps
if you're not clear well then perhaps
wait decide no I won't go for a walk - I
feel affected now emotionally if I had
to stay here no okay so now it probably
wasn't trying to resist any restlessness
then you can go for a walk and that's
the only method you can really do just
keep questioning whatever you're about
to do now is this right or wrong or
something I know just where is it routed
right or wrong has been sort of dealt
with on the level of vinaya but now it's
Anna practical I've already saluted
because the same thing externally can
sometimes be wholesome something
unwholesome depending on whether it's
rooted in your desire or not motivation
and not expecting to help the answer
immediately exactly discerning it that's all they've
exactly discerning it that's all they've
been doing if I don't again is because
of this okay fine but why am i doing it
right now where what is it that that
motivates me to go and want to go for a
walk I have no particular reason okay
that's it that's an answer that
presented itself so I have no particular
reason so that no particular reason is
it possible the truth it may be me
feeling uncomfortable in the kitchen my
own start investigating of course is it
gonna be on holes I'm not clear okay
that is a starting point is this lack of
clarity rooted in a whole so then when
you realize that you really don't mind
even if somebody said oh you can go for
a walk if you decide not to go for work
and you're not gonna be affected if you
have to stay in the Kuti there is okay
well maybe wasn't rooted in that then or
rather you know it wasn't rooted in that
so then you don't need to find I must
find where exactly it's rooted no all
you need to find is that it's not rooted
in a wholesome everything else will be
fine
and that's how you will also avoid
psychologizing because he comes using
we'll be focusing providing the content
the reason you don't you don't need the
reason you just want to make sure that
the absence of these reasons are not
caused by greed aversion delusion that's
it
yeah that's where we do it begins
interrogation hmm interrogate yeah yeah
you can like like this of course it's
basically well we recorded it so you get
a like a reference collected so people
can listen including ourselves you
listen to that okay yeah it reminds you
how to do it but it's a practice you
should be doing to yourself all the time
so now when will you go or everyone goes
to they don't quitting on their own in
the afternoon and sort of you're about
to do something oh is this awesome
no just okay I'm about to do this why
why we're doing it
yeah I bother any red flags coming up
shame is shameful badness okay so
basically just checking peripherally if
there are red flags not necessarily
trying to interfere or control when
you're about to do so again say you go
back to cutting now you finish eating
and then I will go for a walk there's no
problem with that but there's mean you
should do it immediately by default no
you ask yourself why where is this
section routed I know looking for faults
I'm just looking for clarity so it's
rooted in the fact that I'm getting
quite sleepy and I don't want to sleep
going out in a cold air in the wind
walking a bit well certainly well yeah
or at least has a greater chance of
waking me up then if I don't do it then
you do it it's nothing I've also valid
but if it's purely holster reason
because I heard there people on the road
down there I heard voices and I just
want to see what it was and maybe talk
to people and then there becomes clearly
oh that's that's why you want to do it
you realize that would you lean into
that which you're hoping for and if
you're unsure or is it or not what if I
were to go walking in the opposite
direction when I know there is nobody
what I feel dejected and I can't of it
then you realize yes because I had to
desire basically to go down to talk to
people on the pretext of having a
healthy walk and it's nothing like ohad
you you just need to ask yourself and
then look and wait for the answer it's
there because otherwise you wouldn't had
that thought of going for a walk where
the people are
if
was a rooted in their motivation so it's
not it's it nobody can say all that
beyond me this practice is beyond me if
you could truly be on you means you're
incapable of act acting and intending
and nobody is incapable of that which
mean everybody's capable of being aware
of the motivation of those acts and if
it's unwholesome don't do it if it's
also good that all you have to do and
that's what we have said millions of
times that which you know it sounds
skillful abandoning me to new is
skillful cultivated and what is skillful
and careful it's whether it's rooted in
greed over delusion your mind or not
that's it interrogation oh I must do
this and then and then I practice there
is your practice uprooting any uprooting
the maintenance of unskillful states of
mind that are maintaining through the
unskillful actions because you can't
have unskillful action being performed
without the unskillful intention in the
mind persisting with it but you can
certainly approve the unskillful
intention your mind by abstaining from
performing unskillful actions with your
body and speech